{"tossups": [{"question": "The events at this location became widely known fifty years later thanks to a book by Stuart Lake. The incident here resulted in the death of Tom and Frank McLaury as well as Billy Clanton, though the \"law\" side suffered no casualties among Doc Holliday or Wyatt Earp. For 10 points, name this place in Tombstone, Arizona where an 1881 \"shootout\" took place.", "answer": "the <b><u>O.K. Corral</u></b> [or answers like \"an alley near the <b><u>O.K. Corral</u></b>,\" for people who believe sources making the distinction; or <b><u>Tombstone</u></b>, Arizona until it is read]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The proposal to join this body was opposed in the Lodge Reservations, which specifically objected to Article X (ten) of its charter, committing all members to repel any aggression against one. William Borah's Irreconcilables movement drummed up public resistance to American participation in this organization. For 10 points, name this ineffective international body created by the Treaty of Versailles, which the U.S. never joined despite Woodrow Wilson's protestations.", "answer": "<b><u>League of Nations</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Following Ross Perot's most successful attempt at the Presidency, Perot embarked on a campaign against this legislation, predicting it would cause a \"giant sucking sound.\" This legislation was championed in a televised debate by Al Gore, and its architects included Carlos Salinas and Brian Mulroney. For 10 points, name this continental trade pact.", "answer": "<b><u>NAFTA</u></b> [<b><u>North American Free Trade Agreement</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man launched the anti-hunger Operation Breadbasket as a project of his \"Rainbow/PUSH\" coalition. In the 1980s, he ran for the Democratic Presidential nomination twice and was dogged by reports of anti-Semitism during the New York primary. For 10 points, name this former confidante of Martin Luther King, Jr. who became a prominent civil rights spokesman.", "answer": "Jesse <b><u>Jackson</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "When it became apparent that this event had failed, a disgusted Erich Ludendorff simply walked away, leading its main organizer to be sentenced to the Landsberg, where <em>Mein Kampf</em> was written. For 10 points, name this failed 1923 attempt by Adolf Hitler to seize power in Germany by leading an uprising at a Munich drinking venue.", "answer": "<b><u>Beer Hall Putsch</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man's great-grandfather raised the 1st Mississippi Partisan Rangers in the Civil War and wrote <em>The White Rose of Memphis</em>. This author used that ancestor as the model for the protagonist of <em>The Unvanquished</em>, Colonel Sartoris. For 10 points, name this Mississippi-born novelist of \"A Rose for Emily\" and <em>The Sound and the Fury</em>.", "answer": "William <b><u>Faulkner</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "This man said he planned to use a K\u00e4rcher pressure-washer to \"clean out\" suburbs. In 2014, this former leader of the UMP was questioned by police for alleged corruption in a judicial appointment in Monaco. He lost a close re-election bid in 2012 to his left-wing rival Fran\u00e7ois Hollande (<b>pr. frah-SWAH oh-LAHND</b>). For 10 points, name this former President of France.", "answer": "Nicolas <b><u>Sarkozy</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Florida developer Henry Flagler got rich as a business partner of this man. Frederick Taylor Gates advised him on how to direct his philanthropy, which included providing the startup funds for Spelman College and the University of Chicago. For 10 points, name this businessman who was attacked by Ida Tarbell as a monopolist after founding Standard Oil.", "answer": "John D. <b><u>Rockefeller</u></b> [John Davison Rockefeller, Sr.]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 2014, a Senate candidate from this state was criticized for posting graphic X-rays on his website; that second cousin of Barack Obama, Milton Wolf, failed to win the Republican nomination here. This state is where independent Greg Orman is seeking to unseat incumbent Pat Roberts. For 10 points, name this state governed by Sam Brownback from Topeka.", "answer": "<b><u>Kansas</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "An early practitioner of this art form was satirized as \"elevating\" it from a hot-air balloon in an engraving by Honor\u00e9 Daumier (<b>pr. oh-no-RAY dow-mee-EY</b>). This art form was used to depict <em>The Steerage</em> by Alfred Stieglitz and <em>Moon and Half Dome</em> by a later American leader of f/64 (\"eff sixty-four\"). For 10 points, name this art form used by Ansel Adams to produce prints.", "answer": "<b><u>photography</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In 1850, a seeming discrepancy in this scientist\u2019s work was resolved by Stanislao Cannizzaro. This man\u2019s breakthrough was realizing the distinction between atoms and molecules in a gas, causing this veteran of the Piedmont uprising to be the namesake of the number 6.022 times 10 to the 23rd. For 10 points, identify this discoverer of the number of particles in a mole.", "answer": "Amadeo <b><u>Avogadro</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {}, {"question": "This queen came to the throne at age six, leading to the creation of a regency council dominated by Axel Oxenstierna (<b>pr. OCK-sens-TURR-nuh</b>). In 1654, this queen shocked Europe by abdicating her throne and converting to Catholicism, after which she lived out her life in Rome. For 10 points, name this daughter of Gustavus Adolphus, an \u201cenlightened monarch\u201d of Sweden.", "answer": "Queen <b><u>Christina</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The Eighth Amendment to the U.S. Constitution copied nearly verbatim this text\u2019s prohibition on \u201cexcessive bail and cruel and unusual punishments.\u201d This document guaranteed freedom of speech and the right to bear arms, and it also banned Catholics from succeeding to the throne.  For 10 points, name this 1689 law which outlined liberties prior to the Glorious Revolution.", "answer": "<b><u>English Bill of Rights</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>Bill of Rights</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This god's oracle was located at Dodona. Phidias used the ivory-and-gold material chryselephantine to depict this god for one of the Wonders of the Ancient World. This god was believed to have survived the cannibalism of his father Cronus by being swapped with a stone. For 10 points, name this thunder god and head of the Greek pantheon.", "answer": "<b><u>Zeus</u></b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "This man was approached by Thomas Edison's agent Theo Wangemann in 1889, leading him to make the first-ever audio recording by a leading composer. This composer relied on Martin Luther's translation of the Bible as the text for his <em>German Requiem</em>. For 10 points, name this composer whom Hans von Bulow first grouped with Beethoven and Bach as the \"Three Bs.\"", "answer": "Johannes <b><u>Brahms</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This politician purged opponents in the \"Anti-Rightist Campaign\" after encouraging dissenters to identify themselves in the Hundred Flowers movement. Following news of the Secret Speech, this politician led his country away from Nikita Khrushchev's Soviet Union in the late 1950s. For 10 points, name this Long March leader and longtime \"chairman\" of Communist China.", "answer": "<b><u>Mao</u></b> Zedong [or <b><u>Mao</u></b> Tse-tung]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This theory was advocated by John Needham due to a faulty experimental design. Lazzaro Spallanzani argued against this theory by showing that Needham had failed to entirely seal the boiled flask used before observing \u201canimalcules.\u201d For 10 points, name this theory finally put to rest by Louis Pasteur, which holds that rotting food directly creates life.", "answer": "<b><u>spontaneous generation</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {}, {"question": "In 1905, Germany's Kaiser Wilhelm II landed at this country's port of Tangier to support its independence, causing a crisis with France. This country is also home to the headgear namesake Fez and to the site of a January 1943 Allied summit that first formulated the \"unconditional surrender\" doctrine. For 10 points, name this country which hosted the Casablanca Conference.", "answer": "<b><u>Morocco</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This body was originally under the influence of John Pym and the radical \"Five</u></b> <b><u>Members,\" and it was convened to raise money following the Bishops' Wars. This body</u></b> <b><u>steadily lost members, ending up named sardonically for Nicholas (+)</u> Barebones, after its moderate delegates were removed in Pride's Purge to create the (*)</b> Rump Parliament. For 10 points, name this Parliament which oversaw the English Civil War and is named because it sat from 1640 to 1660.", "answer": "<b><u>Long</u></b> Parliament", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man expanded his Keystone Bridge Company into his business empire, which</u></b> <b><u>greatly profited from introducing the Bessemer process to widespread use in America. This</u></b> <b><u>man's 1899 article \"The (+)</u> Gospel of Wealth\" outlined his philanthropic plans, which included founding several (*)</b> library systems now named for him. For 10 points, name this Scottish immigrant who became the greatest steel magnate of the late nineteenth century.", "answer": "Andrew <b><u>Carnegie</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Alexey Leonov posits that the training crash which killed this man in 1968 was caused by</u></b> <b><u>an accidental near-miss with another fighter jet. This man, who was selected out of twenty</u></b> <b><u>candidates from (+)</u> Star City, whistled the patriotic song \"The Motherland Hears\" while re-entering the atmosphere aboard (*)</b><em>Vostok 1.</em> For 10 points, name this Soviet cosmonaut who, in 1961, became the first human to leave the Earth's atmosphere.", "answer": "Yuri <b><u>Gagarin</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>A 2001 panel of experts in this sport named Regla Torres and Lorenzo Bernardi among</u></b> <b><u>its three best players of all time. William Morgan invented this game in 1895 as a less</u></b> <b><u>physical use of (+)</u> basketball courts. Al Scates is the most successful coach in this sport, and was the trainer of the generally regarded best-ever player at this sport, (*)</b> Karch Kiraly. For 10 points, name this game in which a libero, blockers, and setters play across an elevated net.", "answer": "<b><u>volleyball</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>John Brooks Henderson was the initial special prosecutor in charge of resolving this</u></b> <b><u>scandal, but was replaced with James Broadhead after appearing too incorruptible. This</u></b> <b><u>scandal was organized in St. Louis and involved personal (+)</u> secretary Orville Babcock. Treasury secretary Benjamin (*)</b> Bristow exposed this affair in 1875. For 10 points, name this scandal involving the embezzlement of tax revenues on liquor which came to discredit the Grant administration.", "answer": "<b><u>Whiskey Ring</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A road extending from Castrum Truentinum to the Aurelian Walls of Rome was named</u></b> <b><u>for this substance, whose transportation was the impetus for building some of the oldest</u></b> <b><u>known (+)</u> roads. This substance was traded to the north in exchange for gold from the (*) </b>African interior, especially by the Ghana empire. For 10 points, identify this formerly valuable substance which can now be easily retrieved from natural sources such as seawater and is often iodized.", "answer": "<b><u>salt</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man successfully completed the \"red line\" map as part of the plan for a \"Cape to</u></b> <b><u>Cairo railway.\" This man was sent as the agent of the Rothschild company to (+)</u></b> <b>Kimberley, where he spent seventeen years buying competing diamond fields. He founded the (*)</b> De Beers company to cement his monopoly over the industry. For 10 points, name this British colonialist in South Africa who endowed a series of scholarships for foreign students at Oxford.", "answer": "Cecil <b><u>Rhodes</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Guns fired from this building ended the Battle of the Faubourg St. Antoine (</u></b><u>pr. foo-BOO</u> <u>sont AHN-twan</u><b><u>) during the Fronde. This building is where the Marquis de (+)</u> Sade enraged crowds by claiming a plot to massacre its inhabitants. Only seven politically unimportant (*) </b>prisoners were found inside when it was stormed on July 14, 1789. For 10 points, name this Paris prison which was destroyed to start the French Revolution.", "answer": "the <b><u>Bastille</u></b>  <b>NHBB C 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 8 </b> <b>Tiebreakers/extras </b> <b><u>In 1595, the Tooth of the Buddha was moved to a reliquary on this island, where the</u></b> <b><u>Kingdom of Kandy long held out against colonization. In the twentieth century, this island</u></b> <b><u>had the world's first (+)</u> female prime minister, and its (*)</b> Sinhalese majority fought a protracted war with a terrorist group that invented suicide bombing. For 10 points, name this island country where the Tamil Tigers fought against the government at Colombo, often spilling into nearby India.  ANSWER: Sri <b><u>Lanka</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}